Part 4 You will hear part of an Environmental Studies
lecture on tree planting. First, you have some time to look at questions 31 to 40.
Part 5 You will hear part of an Environmental Studies lecture on tree planting. First, you have some time to look at questions 31 to 40.
Now listen carefully and answer questions 31 to 40.
Tree planting now dominates political and popular agendas, and is often presented as
an easy answer to the climate crisis, as well as a way for business corporations to offset
their carbon emissions. But unfortunately, tree planting isn't as straightforward as
some people think. When the wrong trees are planted in the wrong place, it can do considerably
more damage than good, failing to help either people or the environment.
Reforestation projects are currently being undertaken on a huge scale in many countries,
but it's crucial that the right trees are selected. A mix of species should always
be planted, typical of the local natural forest ecosystem, and including rare and endangered
species in order to create a rich ecosystem. It's important to avoid non-native species
that could become invasive. Invasive species are a significant contributor to the current
global biodiversity crisis, and are often in competition with native species and may
threaten their long-term survival. Restoring biodiversity that will maximise carbon capture
is key when reforesting an area, but ideally any reforestation project should have several
goals. These could include selecting trees that can contribute to wildlife conservation,
improve the availability of food for the local community, and maintain the stability of soil
systems. Meeting as many of these goals as possible, whilst doing no harm to local communities,
native ecosystems and vulnerable species, is the sign of a highly successful tree planting
scheme. To ensure the survival and resilience of a planted forest, it's vital to use tree
seeds with appropriate levels of genetic diversity, the amount of genetic variation found within
a species essential for their survival. Using seeds with low genetic diversity generally
lowers the resilience of restored forests, which can make them vulnerable to disease and unable to
adapt to climate change. Choosing the right location for reforestation projects is as
important as choosing the right trees. Ultimately, the best area for planting trees would be in
formerly forested areas that are in poor condition. It's better to avoid non-forested landscapes,
such as natural grasslands, savannas or wetlands, as these ecosystems already contribute greatly
to capturing carbon. It would also be advantageous to choose an area where trees could provide
other benefits, such as recreational spaces. Reforesting areas which are currently exploited
for agriculture should be avoided, as this often leads to other areas being deforested.
Large-scale reforestation projects require careful planning. Making the right decisions
about where to plant trees depends on having the right information. Having detailed and up-to-date
maps identifying high-priority areas for intervention is essential. Drone technology
is a useful tool in helping to prioritise and monitor areas of degraded forest for restoration.
In Brazil, it's being used to identify and quantify how parts of the Amazon are being
devastated by human activities, such as rearing cattle and illegal logging.
A good example of where the right trees were picked to achieve a restored forest
is in Lampang province in northern Thailand. A previously forested site which had been degraded
through mining was reforested by a cement company, together with Chiang Mai University.
After spreading 60 centimetres of topsoil, they planted 14 different native tree species,
which included several species of fig. Figs are a keystone species because of the critical role
they play in maintaining wildlife populations. They are central to tropical reforestation projects
as they accelerate the speed of the recovery process by attracting animals and birds which
act as natural seed dispersers. This helps to promote diversity through the healthy regrowth
of a wide range of plant species. Unlike the majority of fruit trees, figs bear fruit all year
round, providing a reliable food source for many species. At this site for example, after only three
rainy seasons, monkeys started visiting to eat the fig fruits, naturally dispersing seeds through
defecation. Reforestation projects should always aim to make sure that local communities are
consulted and involved in the decision-making process. The restoration of mangrove forests
in Madagascar is an example of a project which has succeeded in creating real benefits for the community.
Destruction of the mangrove forests had a terrible impact on plant and animal life and also badly
affected the fishing industry, which was a major source of employment for local people living in
coastal areas. The reforestation project involved hiring local people to plant and care for the new
mangrove trees. Millions of mangrove trees have now been planted, which has resulted in the return
of a healthy aquatic ecosystem. The mangroves also act as a defence against the increased threat of
flooding caused by climate change. What's more, the local economy is more stable and thousands
more Madagascans are now able to send their children to school. One other important point to consider...
That is the end of part four. You now have one minute to check your answers to part four.